

Summary

I'm a PhD student at Universitat Pompeu Fabra under the joint supervision of Gemma Boleda and Laia Mayol. My PhD research currently focuses on understanding the use of referring expressions, mainly through quantitative and computational methods.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra Ph.D. CANDIDATE IN LINGUISTICS

Barcelona, Spain

2019 - present

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

M.S. IN THEORETICAL AND APPLIED LINGUISTICS

2018 - 2019

• GPA: 8.68/10

· Venue: Computational Linguistics

Beijing Jiaotong University, Complutense University of Madrid

Beijing, China

B.S. IN HISPANIC PHILOLOGY

2014 - 2018

· GPA: 9.58/10

· with Honors

European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information

Virtually

2021

• Track: Language and Computation (LaCo)

Publication

Liao. (2022). Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data. Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung 26, to appear.

Aina, L., Liao, X., Boleda, G., Westera, M. (2021, November). Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution. In Proceedings of the 25th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (pp. 454-469).

Presentation

Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2021

Barcelona, Spain

TALK

December 22nd, 2021

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [Recording]

UR-Ling workshop Barcelona, Spain

November 12th, 2021

· Title: Referent predictability and referential choice

The SIGNLL Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL) 2021

Virtually

POSTER PRESENTATION

November 11th, 2021

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [PDF], [Poster]

Sinn und Bedeutung 26

Virtually

September 9th. 2021

- Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data
- OSF

Workshop on Computational and Experimental Explanations in Semantics and **Pragmatics**

European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021, Virtually

August 10th. 2021

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

Student session in European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021

Virtually

August 6th. 2021

2020 - 2021

· Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

Teaching _____

Semàntica i Pragmàtica (Professor: Martina Wiltschko)

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR MASTER COURSES

- Compositionality and Truth(conditions)
- Modality and possible worlds; Quantifiers
- · Clausal and nominal reference
- Presuppositions
- The Gricean program. Recognizing intentions.
- · What we do when we use language: Speech act theory.
- Dynamic theories of meaning. Language in interaction.
- Expressing emotions and other non-truth-conditional meaning.
- The relation between language, thought and communication

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu

Introducció a la Universitat i Recursos (Professor: Núria Bel)

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR UNDERGRADUATE COURSES

- · Build an HTML website
- · Regular expressions
- · Corpus analysis

Fabra

2020 - 2022

Professional Service

ESSLLI 2022 Student Session

CO-CHAIR

• Track: Language and Computation (LaCo)

Galway, Ireland

August 8-19, 2022

REtreat for Students in Computational Linguistics (REST-CL)

ORGANIZER

· Rural house

Barcelona, Spain

April 11-14, 2022

Work Experience _____

China's Commerce Ministry, Beijing Jiaotong University Training Center

Beijing, China

CHINESE-SPANISH INTERPRETER & TRANSLATOR IN SEMINARS FOR FOREIGN DELEGATIONS

2017 - 2018

- Bilateral Seminar of Infrastructure Between China and Uruguay.
- Seminar on Ocean Railway Construction for Perú-Brasil

Beijing, China

CHINESE TEACHER FOR FOREIGNERS

2017 - 2018

· Teaching elementary Chinese.

Fellowships

Cielo Education

2020.5-2023.5 FI Scholarship awarded by AGAUR (Agency for Management of University and Research Grants) 2019.9-2020.5 CSC Scholarship awarded by Chinese Scholarship Council

XIXIAN LIAO · RÉSUMÉ APRIL 10, 2022

LANGUAGES Mandarin Chinese (native), English (IELTS C1), Spanish (DELE C1)	
SKILLS Python, R, HTML, Visual Basic	
Courses	
Machine Learning Coursera	Standford, online September 20, 2020
• [Certificate]	
The FIDU (Initial Training in University Teaching) Programme in Translation and	Online
Language Sciences Universitat Pompeu Fabra	September 21th 2020 - June 30th 2021
• [Certificate]	.,
From Draft to Submission: Publishing an Article or Book Chapter in English	Online
UNIVERSITAT POMPEU FABRA • [Certificate]	February 2021
Statistics for Language studies	Online
UNIVERSITAT POMPEU FABRA • [Certificate]	May 2021
Participation in Conferences	
The 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	November 7-11, 2021
Sinn und Bedeutung 26	September 8-10, 2021
GeCKo symposium: Integrating Generic and Contextual Knowledge	May 18th, 2020
The 28th edition of the Conference of the Student Organisation of Linguistics in Europe (ConSOLE 28)	January 29-31, 2020
Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2019	December 19-20, 2019
Membership in Scientific Association	
Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)	2021 - present

Languages & Skills _____